Guide to the Homestead First United Methodist Church Records, 1878-1995 AIS.1996.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Homestead First United Methodist Church Records
1878-1995
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Homestead First United Methodist Church (Homestead, Pa.)
AIS.1996.01
2 microfilm_reels
This collection contains eight record books from the church, dating from 1878 and going to 1995 when the church was closed. The collection also contains meeting minutes from various organizations within the church, weekly bulletins, anniversary programs, photographs, newspaper clippings, memorial service programs, as well as information from other local Methodist churches.
History
The Homestead First United Methodist Church was founded in March 1878 and at the time was called the Homestead Methodist Church. The church was founded at the same time the town of Homestead was growing from the influx of immigrant laborers. The members of the Homestead Methodist Church originally met in the Lutheran Church located on Fourth Ave. until the Homestead Bank and Life Insurance Co. donated two lots for the building of a church, one on Ann St. and one on Sixth Ave. The lots were exchanged for two contiguous lots on Ann St. between Sixth Ave. and Seventh Ave. Building for the new church began in 1880.
The new building was dedicated on February 11, 1883. It was at this point that the church changed its name to the Stewart Methodist Episcopal Church, in honor of Joseph S. Stewart who was a founder of the church. This building did not last long, owing to a fire on January 9, 1887. The fire was thought to have been caused by natural gas that had recently been introduced to the furnaces in the church, but was never verified.
A temporary tabernacle was constructed on a vacant lot beside the P.McK. and Y.R.R. Station. It was used as a temporary place of worship, until the dedication of the new church in 1888. This temporary structure was used afterwards for various community purposes.
A new church was built on the corner of Ann St. and Fourth Ave. Mr. Stewart declined to have his name incorporated as the name of the new church. This time the church's name was changed to the Homestead Methodist Episcopal Church. Dedication ceremonies were held on August 5, 1888.
This building was used until 1911, at which point the lots on the corner of Ann St. and Tenth Ave. were purchased. A new building was erected and was dedicated on October 22, 1911. The Homestead First United Methodist Church remained at this location until its closing on December 27, 1995.
Scope and Content
This collection reflects the activities of the members of the Homestead First United Methodist Church, 1878-1995. It also includes information about other local Methodist churches from 1968-1974.
The collection consists of two reels of microfilm in which eight record books are located, program pamphlets, meeting minutes, photographs, weekly bulletins, newspaper clippings, histories of other Methodist churches as well as a history of Methodism in the Steel Valley area.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were microfilmed with the permission of the Homestead First United Methodist Church in 1996.
Previous Citation
Homestead First United Methodist Church Records, AIS.1996.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Homestead First United Methodist Church, ais 96:1, Records, 1878-1995, Archives of Industrial Society, Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh
Churches and Synagogues; Homestead (Pa.) -- History; Methodist Church -- Pennsylvania -- Monongahela River; Methodist Church -- Pennsylvania -- Homestead; Homestead First United Methodist Church (Homestead, Pa.)
- Books, 1868-1995; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains the church's books on membership, attendence, and history. Book #2 contains records from 1883 to 1888 that were destroyed in fire.
  - Book #1, 1868-1883 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Book #2, 1881-1911 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Book #3, 1893-1920 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Book #4, 1921 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Book #5, 1919-1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Book #6, 1942-1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 1)
  - Book #7, 1951-1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Book #8, 1893-1995 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
- Records and Manuscripts, 1885-1992; II.
  Series II consists of church records in the form of program pamphlets, meeting minutes, photographs, weekly bulletins, newspaper clippings, histories of other Methodist churches as well as a history of Methodism in the Steel Valley area. Of particular interest is the program of the Women's Home Missionary Society. This program lists the officers, committees, meeting dates, discussion topics, and hostesses of the society from 1920-1921.
  - Chronological record of Methodism in Steel Valley (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - History of the First Methodist Episcopal Church of Homestead (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Article, July 23, 1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Photograph, January 5, 1973 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - 90th Anniversary Program with Picture (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Dedication program, October 22-26, 1911 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - 90th Session of Pittsburgh Annual Service Program, October 1913 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Weekly Bulletin, December 22, 1914 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Women's Home Missionary Society Program, 1920-1921 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Weekly Bulletin, July 14, 1918 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Memorial Service Program, May 27, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Program, December 19, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Photographs, December 2, 1992 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Homestead Methodism Supplement III, May 14-24, 1970 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Newsletter, May 1968 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Baldwin community Methodist Church 25th Anniversary program, 1943-1968 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Whitaker United Methodist Church 50th Anniversary program, February 3, 1974 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Photograph, circa, 1885 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Certificate of Membership, January 2, 1905 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1916-1922 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1913-1915 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Men's Bible Class, 1933-1936 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1915-1917 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - First Financial Statement, 1919-1920 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Photographs, 1923 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - 50th Anniversary program, October 21-28, 1928 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - History of Church, October 1928 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Play Script (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Register from 50th Anniversary, October 1928 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - 75th Anniversary Attendance, October 18-25, 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Brotherhood Class 25th Anniversary, 1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - 100th Anniversary, September 22-24, 1978 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)
  - Information Booklet, January 1991 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 7, Reel 2)